Let's go back
to our wristwatch example.
As a reminder, it
looks like this so far.
The hour and minute display, or
count, are implemented in parallel regions.
We had used such a broadcast effect that when
the minute counter here jumps from 59 to 0,
it triggers an hour effect that
causes the hour count to advance here.
We had used an
effect to say that
whenever the minute counter goes to
zero, there should be a beep.
We have the alarm on and off
setting, and we have these transitions between these
two composite states to get from
the time display to the alarm setting
and back, and to change between
on and off in the alarm setting.
Are
we done?
No, there
are still problems.
Namely, one major problem is that
when we return to the time display
from the alarm setting,
it always jumps to zero.
Why
is that?
We had discussed last
what the consequences of
these entry/exit
options are.
And for example,
here's what it's like:
Suppose we are
somehow sitting at 2:58,
so we have state 2 in the hour
count and state 58 in the minute count.
Then button a is pressed,
so this trigger is fired.
What does
it do?
We had said we leave the
overall state, that is, we leave both
regions, we end up here in the
alarm state in the first moment at
the on sub-state, because that's the start state;
then maybe we turn the alarm on and
off several times (that's where we would use
b to switch back and forth between these
two sub-states), then we press a
again, so we trigger the a trigger.
What would
that do?
We would leave that sub-state, go
back to that more complex region
state, and we would do
that with the default entry.
And that means that in each
region, we would choose the initial state.
Then we end up back at
zero and zero, instead of 2:58.
That's not intentional, of course, and
that's also true the other way around.
So whatever was going on last in the
alarm setting, so to speak, is ignored when
we switch to the
time display and back.
What makes
this clear?
We have a time, we switch with a
to the alarm setting, then that is first On,
then we press b, are Off, then we press
button a, then we get back into this region state,
switch there maybe a few times,
press button a again at some point.
What
happens then?
We leave that right state,
get into the left state, use
the default entry
there, and that says
we start back at the
start state from that hierarchical state.
So we're back at On, even though the
last time we were here in the sub-state, we
were in this left state,
we chose the sub-state Off.
So these transitions in this
way (as used before) forget what
was in each
of the sub-states.
This is not surprising because
we are not using the history,
which was actually introduced precisely for
the purpose of not forgetting such sub-states.
We have used here in this example
so far only the exit from the
total state and the
standard entry into composite states.
And that just doesn't exhaust the possibilities
we have for not forgetting sub-states (i.e., the
last state in a hierarchical
state or a region state).
So, the problems were to be expected
because we haven't used history nodes yet.
And the solution, of course, is
to actually use entries over history.
In fact, in the
specific example, it doesn't
even matter if we
use shallow or deep history.
Why?
Well, because there are no
deep nesting levels here at all.
So both the right region state
and the left hierarchical state have
exactly one more nesting level
and no deeper hierarchical nestings
where it would make a difference
whether we use deep or shallow history.
I'll use the shallow
history here in a moment.
Since we have two regions to go
to when we transition to the right
region state, we actually need two history
states, one in each of the two regions.
And the jumping on entering
is then realized by a fork.
So here from right to left we
can say we're introducing a flat history here
and this a transition we just
go to the history node here.
Going from left to right,
yes we want to enter these
two regions, and in both
regions we want to use that
we could remember what the
last hour or minute state was.
Because we have a going
to the right via a
fork each to history nodes
in the two regions entering.
And that then
looks like this.
Nothing has changed in
the substates, for example
this region is as before,
this one is as well.
These history nodes
have been added.
Flat history, because there
is no star on it.
The entry to the right happens via
this fork, which then points to the
two history nodes, and from right to
left we also go via a history node.
If we compare this picture
with this diagram, we can see
exactly where the differences are, so
the two right and left total
states have not changed significantly,
but the transitions are now
more precisely designed and ensure
that we remember just sub-states.
Now it would be like, if we say we're
going to be at 2: 58 o'clock in the hour
display, would then switch to the alarm setting state with
a, that will be the first time we go to
On because the history node has this arrow on On,
then we can switch me back and forth with b
several times or not, would then go back
to the region state right with a, but would
not do that via the default entry,
but would use per this fork these
history nodes and then it would be the same
when we go back that we don't go to
zero here because we've been in this region,
this overall state before, namely at 2: 58,
d. That is, these two history
nodes would ensure that when we return
to this right complex state, we would be
at 2: 58 and not at 0: 00.
And vice versa, if we switched here
to Off, then press a to return here
to the hour and minute
display and then press a
again and again, then we would not land
at On, but wherever we were last in the
left hierarchical state and if that was Off,
then we would also land at Off, i.e.
these two problems mentioned here
would be solved exactly by this.
As said, here we could have used
in each case also deep history, because
there is no deeper nesting
at all on the one hand.
On the other hand, we
would not have needed to
draw the arrows that
start from history nodes.
These three arrows are only used if we have
never been in the respective state in the respective
region or nesting level, if such
a history node has no direct outgoing
arrow, then in each case simply the corresponding
start node from the respective region or nesting
level is taken and since it is
in each case in such a way that
the history nodes always
point anyway to the sub-state,
which is also marked by the
start state in the corresponding place,
the omission of these three
arrows would make no difference.
Especially if, when we first enter a
state via history nodes, we want to go
to a different state than the
start state of that level would
be if we came via
standard entry rather than history.
Those are a couple of variations
that we could have omitted those
three arrows and that we could have
taken deep history instead of shallow history.
So are we done with that, having
gotten from this case to this diagram?
No, there's
still something missing.
What is
still missing?
Well, what hasn't been realized yet is
that this alarm setting really has something
to do with whether or not there is
a click, a transition to a full hour.
Here there is this effect, if
we jump to the 0th minute,
that is to a full hour,
then a signal is triggered here.
Actually, the clock should only trigger the
signal when the alarm is actually set,
but there is no connection or
no communication between the fact, is the
alarm on or off on the one hand,
and the fact, is beeped here or not.
So we have
to transport some more
information and we can
do that via a flag.
This is like a
variable in a programming language,
a variable in which we can
store values, for example a Boolean variable,
which we can switch on and
off, true and false, zero and one.
We will call this AL for
alarm and use it to get this
beep effect, this signal tone under control, i.e.
on the one hand, we should take that into
account when triggering this beep, whether the
alarm is on or not, so we
should check this flag whether it is
on or off on the one hand.
On the other hand, of course, we
have to make sure that it's also set
to on and off at some point,
that is, during these transitions between these
states here of the alarm setting, we
should do something with this alarm flag.
We'll see how that happens in a
moment, what that looks like then, but
the basic idea is, we'll set this
alarm flag, use that when the beep is
triggered to check if that should be, and
set it when it's turned on and off.
Furthermore, by means of this alarm flag, we
will actually also avoid using the flat history
in the alarm setting
sub-state, in the left part.
So if we're going to introduce a flag anyway that
we can look at whether the alarm is on or off,
then we don't need this history node at
all, because we can just as easily just read
this flag decisively at the entry here, whether we
want to go to this state or that state.
What does that
look like then?
With that, we move
on to this diagram.
We can compare that again
with what we have so far.
What
changes there?
So again the main parts, here the
regions don't change or here this inner structure
of this left hierarchical
state, but especially here at
the transitions we do something, namely here instead
of using the history from right to left
we simply make that dependent on these flags
whether we go to the on or off state.
We're allowed to do that by
writing another condition to this trigger.
If you look in the previous slides, you
can see that this is a possible description,
that we have a trigger and another possible
condition and that would be this query again
of this alarm flag, that
has to be set somewhere.
That's what's
happening here.
In switching between two sub-states,
we may also trigger an effect.
So an effect can be
to switch this alarm flag.
So if we switch to Off with the
b button, we set Alarm to zero and
if we switch to On,
we set Alarm to one.
We take advantage of that when we enter
this left setting state by making that dependent
on the alarm flag, whether we want to go
this way or that way and very importantly of course:
We also use the alarm flag here
to trigger that beep, that signal only
when we enter the zero state and
the alarm flag is currently set to one.
Those are differences between
this chart and that chart.
Is that
it then?
Well we still need to somehow determine how
the alarm flag is set at the beginning.
At some point in the
beginning, this overall chart is entered.
We know we start in the hours minutes
display because the start node points to it here.
We choose the default entry for this, which
is the start state for hour minutes 0:00,
but is the alarm flag
set on this or not?
That still needs
to be clarified.
We will do that in a moment
and in the course of that we will
also model the third aspect
right away, that the clock has
a battery that can get empty and when
the battery gets empty, you should replace it.
But in doing so, the hours and
minutes are to be reset to zero.
The clock then starts running again
at zero and the alarm flag,
the alarm should always
be on at the beginning.
This is the place where we also set
whether the alarm is originally on or not.
So we're modeling that the clock
has a battery that can go dead,
needs to be changed, and in that
case something happens to the state, namely
we want, if the battery was
dead, then we don't want to enter
the states, for example, through the
history, but at 0:00, one aspect.
The
other aspect:
We want that then the alarm flag is set
to one, that is, if you put a new
battery in the clock and also at the
beginning simply the alarm state is always one.
And that could
then achieve so:
So we pack everything that
we have so far in terms
of state diagram, that was this
part, we pack that again into a
hierarchical state, namely how the clock
behaves when the batteries are not empty.
Everything that is here is developed exactly as
before and then we have not parallel to that
but independent of that another state
that is there for when the
battery is empty and when the watch
is delivered the battery compartment is empty
and the battery is empty, that is here
is the extreme beginning of the whole processing.
When a battery is inserted, then on the one
hand we come into this part here and we know
that we then start at this
start state, so we start over the
default entry here at zero and zero and we
set the alarm flag to one in the process.
Then what happens is whatever
the previous behavior was, so
time progresses, we can change
the alarm setting, we can
turn on and off in the process so
it beeps right when the alarm is on.
When we switch back to
the alarm setting, the flag is
used to check whether the alarm
is on or not, and so on.
Then the battery
can always run out.
This causes us to end
up in this state again:
Battery
is empty.
We can only leave this
state by inserting a new battery.
What happens
in the process?
Then we end up
at 0:00 again, as
we would expect after losing the
battery and inserting a new one.
We end up at 0:00 because we
don't use the history node, we use
the default entry,
the two sub-start states
0 and 0, and we also always set the alarm
flag to one when we insert a battery, which means
that if we then pressed a for the first
time, we would always end up in that sub-state.
And that's supposed to be our
final modeling for this wristwatch now.
And that's where most of
the elements that we introduced
earlier for UML
state diagrams occur.
There are many more, but they
should not be the topic here.